We often imagine antiquity in a single color-
-But it didn't look.
We have a picture of white antiquity.
That sculptures and architecture were white, but it was painted.
Antiquity is more colorful and dirtier.
Rome's dictator Julius Caesar has the same length of time to today-
-As the completion of the pyramids in Egypt.
We start with the Greek antiquity.
Greece is divided into city states.
They are independent and consist of a city with surrounding landscapes.
Most are farmers.
If they are self -governing - why are we talking about a Greece?
Greeks see themselves as a people, regardless of where they bor-
-And everyone speaks and writes in Greek.
They also share the same god-
-And every four years, Olympic games are held to honor them.
Religion was polytheistic, with many gods.
-Ee to take power from the rich aristocratic family heads-
-and distribute it to more.
This is solved by giving all citizens voting rights.
The parenthesis is that only free, Athenian men are counted as citizens.
In Athens, women, foreigners and slaves also lived.
They had no right of voting or the right to speak in this system.
It is a democratic principle, but not a democracy like today.
Elections were not seen as a democratic institution, because they could be influenced.
The lot was the democratic way to choose people.
With it comes rights and obligations.
If you are drawn forward, you are obliged to take your responsibility.
If you are drawn into the council, you need to be able to convince the free Athenian men.
You both need good ideas and be a skilled speaker.
Many philosophers were also a teacher of rhetoric.
The collective went before-
-And the whole community was organized according to the best of the state.
Citizens were some kind of warrior.
War characterizes the entire life of the Spartans, and they conquer land.
You should always be ready for battle, and loss is nothing that is accepted.
Boys are raised by the state and do military service until they are thirty.
For people in Sparta, the state and the collective are at the center.
One should live a sparse life.
One would live spartan.
You looked down at material wealth, so you would live poor.
The city states differ, but nothing unites as an external enemy.
One of these has the city states in the east: the Persian Empire.
The Persians are an arch enemy of the Greek world.
Athens and Sparta are side by side against the Persians in several wars.
At Thermopyle, Greece goes on a loss, and you dream of revenge.
When Alexander the Great inherits power in the Greek Kingdom of Macedonia-
-he thinks revenge.
He leaves on an expedition east and is successful.
He conquers the entire Persian kingdom.
Finally he reigns over today's Greece, Turkey-
-Iran, Iraq, Egypt, Afghanistan and India.
It is the mixture between the Greek and the eastern.
A typical such mixture is the coin here.
A side in Greek and one in Persian style.
When it is not war - what is it like in the ancient world?
It was a wonderful period if you were an aristocratic man.
Then they had great fun.
The majority are not free men and do not have great fun.
Slaves have no rights, and often married women away when they are twelve.
The marriage was mainly something man in
-A social and economic reasons.
Love did not matter that much.
The goal was to breed the heirs-
-So you got married heterosexually.
Then you could have other relationships-
-When we might be described as gay or bisexual.
So you didn't think then.
There are strong ideals and norms-
-Dore if you are a woman or a man, free or slave.
A man should be strong and have control.
One had control over one's body, their feelings and lustar-
-And even over others.
After all, they controlled your wife, their children and their slaves.
-And you control areas up to today's United Kingdom.
In addition to the Greek areas, they also take their gods.
They get new, Roman names.
Hello then, Zeus.
Welcome, Jupiter.
But for the people in conquered areas - what happens to them?
How does the life change to belong to the Roman Empire?
A principle is that Rome does not interfere in local affairs-
-or the religious life.
You let people speak the language they speak.
In the eastern part you still speak Greek.
In the Republic of Rome, big cities grow in
-But wherever you live, it gets carbon black as soon as the sun goes down.
Here is a Roman oil lamp - the only light you have except the sun.
You must have many, and it was one of the most common objects.
They are manufactured on running bands in workshops around the kingdom.
The workshops were named after the owner.
The names were printed on the bottom, so you knew where the lamp came from.
It was one of the first objects that were mass -produced.
It is also true that these brands are pirated.
Therefore, Caesar becomes less popular and ultimately murdered by senators.
Then the empire takes over.
Rome is governed by an emperor, and everyone gets the title Augustus.
Now follows a period of 200 years of peace.
Much we recognize now is established: monuments, bridges and aqueducts.
For the Romans, life is quite comfortable, but all good has an end.
It crackles in the joints, and the Roman Empire is in crisis.
The Conquest War has subsided, and they gave all the slaves.
The governing bodies are forced to raise the tax, which deteriorates for farmers.
A new religion emerges: Christianity.
Christians refuse to worship the gods of Rome
-The Christianity is banned and the Christians are persecuted.
But with Emperor Constantine, everything changes.
Constantine perhaps expects the potential of Christianity
-Som something that can hold together the now rather fragmentary empire.
That an era was over - probably not.
There was probably no giant difference-
-But antiquity has been symbolized a wonderful time with philosophy and knowledge.
We have read the philosophers.
They do not tell how they exploit women and slave-
-and how others are treated.
We only got this ideal image from those who were doing well.
The second picture we have had to dig out.
The democratic heritage has been given a great place, and it has often been idealized.
Not least Greek democracy, but it wasn't always.
Only in the 1850s began the ancient democracy-
-Ses as a political role model.
Before that, democracy was regarded as a mob.
The idea of a Roman Empire power has inspired rulers.
Napoleon, Mussolini and Hitler used Roman symbols.
From the first democratic steps in Greece to the military empire in Rome.
In ancient times, different types of rule and view of power may take place.
Whatever you want to legitimize, you can often find it in antiquity.